hello everyone today I'll be talking
about retail site
selection shopping centers in recent
years have faced intense competition
from bigbox stores like Walmart and Ikea
in isolated or strip locations and
online
retailers as a result more shopping
center operators are utilizing social
media to lure and retain
customers when a major traffic
generating store closes then its impact
on the remaining retail tenants
especially when the closed store had a
prominent position in the mall is a
matter of
concern so let's talk about how to
identify right
location identifying the right location
at the right price is critical to the
success of any retailer in addition to
careful plan and budgeting requirements
retailers also need to
consider characteristics of customer
segments shopping at the location this
is critical inide selection firms use
scoring systems to rate quality of the
alternative retail sites on factors like
visibility access population size
household income and
traffic Predictive Analytics can be used
used to forecast sales performance at
low medium and high location quality
retail
sites most importantly retailers must
physically verify the store
location the rent charge for a site
should also be considered and sales
revenue that can be generated from that
site marginal analysis of rent paid
versus increase in store performance can
be used to rule out High sites that are
not worth the
investment understanding current state
of the retail leasing market and
evaluating multiple qualified location
as backup is
advisable Co tenants in a shopping
center or shopping district they should
be resurged pedestrian and vehicular
traffic counts indicate whether cants
are good for the newly arriving
retailers or not lease should be for at
least 5 years or longer than
that coming to the types of
locations there are three different
location types the first one is the
isolated store the second one is the
unplanned business district and the
third is the planed shopping
center an isolated store is a
freestanding retail outlet located on a
highway or a
street there are no adjacent retailers
with which this type of store shares
traffic the advantage of this type of a
retail location is there is no
competition in Clos
proximity there are better Road and
traffic visibility rental cost are low
there is easy parking available cost
reductions can be possible leading to
lower prices but there are some
disadvantages to this type of a retail
location that is the initial customer
can may be difficult to attract as many
people will not travel very far to get
to one store on a continuous
basis there is an increased advertising
expenses and cost such as outside
lightning security the trash collection
or the ground maintenance they are not
shared such a store must often be built
rather than
rented large store formats such as
Walmart Costo both of them are the
American multinational retail
Corporation and in India the best
example can be of
dmart they these stores they are best
suited to isolated
locations because a small specialty
store would be unable to develop a
customer following people would be
unwilling to travel to a store that does
not have a large assortment of products
or a strong image for merchandise and
prizes now now let's talk about the
unplanned business district an unplanned
business district is a type of retail
location where two or more stores are in
close close
proximity for example four April stores
exist in an area with no grocery
store there are four kinds of unplanned
business
districts the first one is the central
business district
the second is the secondary business
district and the third one is the
neighborhood business
district fourth is
string a central business district is a
hub of retailing in a
city where there is a greatest density
of Office Buildings and
stores both vehicular and pedestrian
traffic are very high Shoppers are drawn
from the whole urban area and include
all ethnic groups and all classes of
people has at least one major department
store and a number of specialty and
convenience stores the arrangement of
stores follows no preset format it
depends on first come first
located Central business district or CBD
draw a large number of Shoppers because
of their assessability
to public
transportation there is a wide range of
prices available to the customer there
is high level of pedestrian traffic and
their nearness to Commercial and social
facilities the second is the secondary
business
district SBD is an unplan shopping area
in a city or town that is usually
bounded by the intersection of two major
streets large cities have multiple
sbds the kind of goods and services sold
in an SBD is similar to that of CBD but
a secondary business district has
smaller stores less width and depth of
mercandise Assortment and a smaller
trading area with large proportion of
convenience oriented
items the SPD major major strengths are
access to public transportation less
crowding and more personal service than
in central business district and are
located near to the residential area
than a
CBD the third one is the neighborhood
business district or NBD it's an
unplanned shopping area that appeals to
the convenient shopping and service
needs of a single residential area an
NBD con contains several small stores
such as dry cleaning a stationary store
a beauty Saloon restaurant
Etc this type of business district is
situated on a main major streets of its
residential
area neighborhood business district are
opened at good locations they have long
store hours good parking and less hectic
atmosphere than a central business
district or secondary business district
but there is a limited selection of
goods and services and prices are higher
because competition is less than in SBD
or
CBD the fourth un business district is
termed as string a string is an
unplanned shopping area comprising a
group of retail stores often with
similar or compatible product lines
located along a street or
Highway antique stores appil retailers
car dealers they often situate in
strings a string location has many
advantages they have lower rent more
flexibility better Road visibility
parking and lower operating cost but
they have less product variety there is
a high advertising cost they need to
build their own premises and there are
many zoning restrictions in a string
unplanned business district the third
type of a retail site is a plant
shopping
center plant shopping center includes
variety of retail stores like Banks food
courts theaters service St STS that are
architecturally designed for shopping
with anchor stores and small stores in
between to serve the shopping needs of a
city or
area PL shopping center has maximum
pedestrian traffic for individual stores
because of access to highways and
availability of parking for
consumers generally lower rent and taxes
than Central Business districts and
lower theft rates in the plant shopping
center but they have higher rent than an
isolated store they have restrictions on
goods and services that can be sold by
each store and there is always a
competitive environment within the
center and Domination by large anchor
stores there are three types of plant
shopping center Regional Community and
neighborhood let's talk about the
regional shopping center first it is a
major retail shopping complex serving a
distinct geographical area of a city or
state it has at least one major ful line
department store and number of other
retailers and service
providers a regional center offers a
very Broad and deep assortment of
shopping oriented goods and services
intended to enhance the consumer's
visit re naal shopping center at
category killers and is a result of a
planned effort to recreate the shopping
variety of a suburban
area the second type is the community
shopping center it is a moderate sized
plant shopping facility with a branch
department store a category killer store
as well as several smaller stores it
offers a moderate assortment of shopping
and convenience oriented goods and
services to
Consumers Community shopping center are
of two types the first one in this is
the power center a power center is a
shopping site with category K stores and
a smaller stores and several
complimentary stores specializing in one
product
category the second in this is the
Lifestyle
Center Lifestyle Center is an open air
shopping site that includes new
specialty stores as well as dining and
entertainment the focus is often on
April Home Products music restaurants
and
books the third type of plant shopping
center is the neighborhood shopping
center neighborhood shopping center is a
planed shopping facility with the
largest store being a supermarket or a
drug store other retailers include a
laundry a dry cleaner Bakery stationary
store a beauty parlor or a hardware
store this Center focuses on convenience
oriented goods and services for people
living or working
nearby the decision to select a
locational format whether isolated
unplanned District or planned Center
depends on the firm's strategy and a
careful evaluation of advantages and
disadvantages of each
alternative coming to the next topic
that is location and site
evaluation assessment of Journal
locations and the specific sites
requires extensive
analysis different retailers need
different kinds of sites a location that
is good for one firm may be less
desirable for
another an upscale app should be
benefited from pedestrian traffic which
is close to major department stores or
specialty stores but the convenience
store would be in an area with ample
parking and vehicular traffic it does
not need to be near
stores pedestrian traffic that is most
crucial measure of a location and site's
value and are the number and the type of
people passing by a site with the most
pedestrian traffic is often regarded as
the
best the number and the type of vehicles
driven to a particular shopping area is
crucial for the success of a retail
store
operation convenience stores rely on
heavy vehicular traffic where pedestrian
traffic is often
limited the number and quality of
parking spots their distance from stores
and availability of employee parking
should be evaluated while choosing a
location and doing a site
evaluation access from major highways
and ease of deliveries must be examined
while selecting a site for a retail
store the availability of buses taxies
trains and other kinds of public
transport must always be evaluated
evaluated for any area which is not
readily accessible by vehicular
traffic
visibility visibility of a store is
another important factor to be
considered while selecting store
location a site should be visible by
pedestrian or vehicular
traffic a site on a side street or at
the end of shopping center is not as
visible as one on the major road or at
the center's
entrance high visibility increases store
awareness a corner location may be
desirable because because it is situated
at the intersection of two streets and
has Corner
influence it is usually more expensive
because of Greater pedestrian and
vehicle passes by that is why
restaurants and other retailers they
like and they seek Corner
sides even the stationary stores the
furniture stores they often require the
visibility of their store to increase
their traffic to the store terms of
occupancy should be evaluated
thoroughly whether ownership or
leasing if leasing then type of lease
operations and maintenance cost taxes
zoning restrictions they must be
evaluated for each Pro prospective
site this is all from my side on the
selection of site location for a retail
store thank
you